Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com
그만 버텨라, 바보야
Stop struggling, fool.
오보사에 물렸다
You were struck by
a five- step snake.
His venom moves swiftly.
독이 빨리 퍼진다
대부분은 5발도 못 가서 죽지
Most die before their fifth step.
제 검은 어디 있습니까?
Where is my sword?
가져갔다
Taken away.
통금을 어긴 벌이다
Punishment for breaking curfew.
I need to go, Sifu.
Now.
사부님, 전 지금
당장 가야 합니다
뱀에게 어떻게
복수를 하려느냐?
How do you revenge a snake?
거기에 뱀 하나만 있을 거라
생각하다니 멍청한 놈
You would be a fool to think
only one serpent lays in wait.
더 치명적인 공격이
있을 수도 있다
There is always
a deadlier strike to come.
넘어가도록 해라
One should walk away.
Sifu.
사부
폴로 공
Master Polo.
가만히 있으라
Save your breath.
칸께서 라틴인의 건강에 대해
알아보라고 명령하셨다
The Khan requests
that I inquire as to the Latin's health.
살겠는가?
Will he survive?
아버님께서 기뻐하시겠군
Father will be most pleased.
황자께서는요?
And, um, the Prince?
측은한 마음이 없다면
Without compassion,
어찌 사람과 짐승이
구별될 수 있겠소?
what is there
to distinguish men from beasts?
그대의 제자는 성벽 밖에서
무엇을 하고 있었소?
What was your student
doing beyond the walls?
잠이 오지 않았습니다
Sleep escaped me.
I thought a ride would clear my mind.
말을 타면 정신이
맑아질 것 같았습니다
목구멍에 너무 가까이 물렸군
So close to your throat...
조금만 밑에 물렸으면
독이 심장을 멈추게 했을 거다
A few inches lower,
the venom would have stilled your heart.
Tread carefully, Master Polo.
조심하라, 폴로 공
아니면 영원한 잠에
빠질 수도 있으니
Or you will find yourself
a more permanent sleep.
Great Khan.
대칸이시여
Business forces us
to disturb you.
사정이 급하여
오수를 방해하옵니다
Escort the concubine out.
후궁을 물려라
Leave her to her task.
계속 하게 놔둬라
아들아, 라틴인의
상태는 어떠하냐?
Tell me, son,
what news of the Latin?
송 반란군에 대한 소식을
듣고 싶진 않으시고요?
Would you rather not hear
the news we carry of the Song rebels?
궁금했으면 먼저
물었을 것이다
I would have asked first if I had.
외국인이 생각이 많아
잠을 이루지 못하였다 합니다
The foreigner claims his mind was
muddied with thoughts that hindered sleep.
초원을 달리는 게
도움이 되었으면 했답니다
He hoped a ride in the grasslands
might assist him.
아...
Oh.
무엇 때문에 그리
심란했는지 궁금하구나
I wonder what disturbed him so.
의원은 건강을 완전히
되찾을 거라 하였습니다
The healer promised
a full recovery.
What news of the Song?
송의 소식은?
협상을 제안했습니다
They request a parley.
무슨 목적인지는 알 수 없습니다
To what end,
we do not know.
It seems an auspicious opportunity.
아주 좋은 기회로 보입니다
- 저들은 전쟁을 두려워합니다
- 그 동기를 모르지 않습니까?
They are afraid of war.
An opportunity born of what, though?
It makes little sense
with their current standing.
지금의 상황으로는
이해되지 않는 일입니다
그럼 협상으로 명료해질 것입니다
But the parley will give us clarity.
저들은 폐하를 직접 뵙고자 합니다
They request you personally, Sire.
Perhaps a ruse to take your life.
폐하를 해치려는
계략일 수 있습니다
We must not be deceived.
Prepare to destroy them.
속아선 안 됩니다
저들을 칠 준비를 해야 합니다
특사를 보내 교섭할 것이다
They will make do with emissaries.
The thought of a parley pleases me.
협정을 할 생각에 기분이 좋구나
Jingim's instincts are correct.
진금의 직감이 맞다
Assemble the War Council.
전시 내각을 소집하라
아이와 참 잘 지내지 않는가?
She has quite a way
with the boy, doesn't she?
배려심 깊고, 친절하고...
Caring. Kind.
She is her mother's daughter.
그 어미의 그 딸입니다
Will my mother
come back for me, Uncle?
어머니가 돌아오실까요, 삼촌?
Of course.
그럼
She is simply off learning
to be the best dancer in the world
엄마가 잠깐 떠난 건
세계 최고의 춤을 배우러 간 거란다
- 언젠가 네게 가르쳐줄 거야
- 그래요?
- so she can teach you one day.
- Mmm- hmm.
그럼 내가 세계 최고의
춤꾼이 될 거예요
Then I will be the best dancer
- in the world.
- Mmm- hmm.
'Tis odd...
이상하구려
I've not seen Mei Lin since
the Emperor's spirit left his body.
선황께서 붕어하신 이후
메이린을 보지 못했소
그대의 여동생은
요즘 어디에 있소?
Where does your sister
keep herself now?
아마 예전에 하던 일을 하겠지요
Returned to her old ways, I suspect.
Practicing her art in brothels.
사창가에서 몸을 팔고 있을 겁니다
Mei Lin was cared for
and welcomed in her time here.
메이린은 이곳에서는
기꺼이 환영받고 대접받았소
왜 갑자기 떠난 것이오?
What would drive her away?
재물 때문인가?
Treasure?
재상이 나눠줘도 되지 않았소?
You have enough to share, surely.
전 제 여동생의
보호자가 아닙니다
I am not my sister's protector.
왜요?
Why?
그대가 출세하기 전엔
그대의 보호자이지 않았소?
Was she not yours
in the days before your ascension?
That was a long time ago, Empress.
아주 오래 전 일입니다, 태후마마
그대는 선황께도
그런 표정을 지었던가?
Would such a look have escaped
your face toward my husband?
선황께서 노란수선화를
드신 건 몰랐습니다
I never knew
your husband to eat jonquils.
If it suited him, he would have.
그게 그분께 맞았다면
그리했을 것이오
그럼 더 존경심이 담긴
표정을 지었을 것이오
And you would have worn
a more esteemed look.
내가 황제다!
I am the Emperor!
황제께서 꽃을 드시고
몽골을 억누를 수 있다면야....
If my Emperor could eat flowers
and keep the Mongols in check...
제가 기꺼이 정원을
지어드릴 것입니다
I would gladly serve him a garden.
들여보내 주시오
Let me pass.
무슨 일인가, 외국인?
What's your business, foreigner?
지나가게 해 주시오!
Let me pass!
- 무슨 일이냐고...
- 놔두게
- What's your business...
- Leave him.
코카친과 얘길 해야겠습니다
I need to speak with Kokachin.
망상은 정신을
더럽히는 흠이다
Delusion is an imperfection
that defiles the mind.
꼭 만나야 합니다
I must speak with her, please.
이것이 널 망상에 빠뜨린
뱀이 문 자국이냐?
Is it the serpent's sting
that has deluded you?
다치게 할 의도가 아닙니다
I intend no harm.
자넨 누굴 해칠 만한
능력도 없네, 마르코 공
You are incapable of harm,
Master Marco.
코카친을 지키는 데
좀 더 경계해야 합니다
You need to be more vigilant
in your protection of Kokachin.
위험합니다
She is in danger.
그대가 직면한
위험이나 염려하게
Concern yourself
with the danger you face.
The Blue Princess
is secure in my care.
청공주는 내 보호로
안전하게 계시네
Leave now
or suffer my fate.
나가지 않으면
내 꼴이 될 걸세
제 3의 성을 경험해 보았나, 라틴인?
Have you ever sampled
the third sex, Latin?
네 해 전 겨울 북쪽 군단과의
전투에서 등에 화살을 맞았소
Four winters ago, I took an arrow
in the back fighting the North Hordes.
I tasted blood for two days.
이틀 동안 입에서
피맛을 느꼈지
Great Khan bid me come and see him
when I was finally able to stand.
대칸께서는 내가 일어나
걷기 전까지 알현을 금지하셨소
내가 그분의 친아들인데도
And I'm his own flesh and blood.
황자께선 강하셨죠
You were strong
빨리 회복하셔서
다시 말에 오르셨습니다
and quickly saddled
your own steed again.
정말 용감하셨지요
So brave.
송 반란군과 협정을
할 거란 소식을 들었다
I heard word of a parley
with the Song rebels.
- Is it true?
- It is.
- 사실이냐?
- 네
The War Council assembles.
전시 내각이 소집되었습니다
네가 없는데?
In your absence?
아버님을 기다리는 중입니다
We wait on Father.
어디 계시냐?
Where is he?
눈이 동그란 애완동물을
돌보고 계시겠지요
Surely tending to
his round- eyed pet.
황후께 차를 권하겠느냐
아니면 계속 그리 서 있을 테냐?
Might you offer your Empress tea?
Or will you continue to stand idle?
용서하십시오, 마마
Forgive me, Empress.
그 유럽인은 신경쓰지 말거라, 진금
Spare the Europa no thought, Jingim.
아버님이 네가 더 나은 사람임을
의심하게 해선 안 된다
Do not let your father
doubt you the better man.
I am the better man.
내가 더 나은 사람입니다
더 나은 자는 어두운 곳에서
자신의 여인과 질투를 품고 있진 않는다
The better man does not sit in the dark
with his woman and his jealousies.
더 나은 자라면
똑바로 서서
The better man stands erect and strong
그 시선을 자신의 편으로
돌릴 방법을 모색해야 한다
and finds a way
to tilt the scales in his favor.
진정해야지
Easy, girl.
수베, 오라버니께 보낼 소식이다
Sube.
A message for my brother.
긴급한 일이다
It's urgent.
약속한 바에 따라
서둘러 처리하라
Follow our arrangement
and make fast your horse.
예, 마님
Yes, ma'am.
시다오가 우리 사람을 벤 지
몇 주가 안 되었습니다
Sidao beheaded
our men not weeks ago.
왜 지금 평화를
바라는 겁니까?
Why call for peace now?
He fears the wrath
that comes and seeks to alter course.
분노에 대한 두려움 때문에
그 방향을 바꿨겠지
The man is not circumspect.
Jia Sidao is too arrogant for that.
용의주도한 자가 아닙니다
그러기엔 너무 거만합니다
그의 야망이
그의 자만함이오
His ambition is his arrogance.
하지만 그 재상만이 성벽 도시에서
영향력 있는 자는 아닙니다
But the Chancellor is not the only
mind at work within the Walled City.
그대는 다르게 보는가, 유세프?
You see a different landscape, Yusuf?
Have your spies received
intelligence from Xiangyang?
샹양의 첩자에게서
첩보가 왔는가?
No, Sire.
I rely now on my own.
아닙니다, 제 생각일 뿐입니다
The Boy Emperor
is but five seasons old.
소년 황제는
이제 겨우 다섯 살입니다
His coronation day approaches.
대관식 날이 다가오고 있지요
시다오가 왕족처럼 굴긴 해도
왕좌를 탐하는 자일 뿐입니다
Sidao may play the royal,
but he's a pretender to the throne.
그자가 권력을 탐하지만
왕실의 위치도 혈연도 없습니다
He desires power, but holds
no royal position or blood claim.
그 외에도 권력을 획득하는
방법은 있습니다, 진금 왕자님
There are other ways to secure power,
Prince Jingim.
Are we safe to assume
Jia Sidao takes such steps presently?
지아 시다오가 지금 이런
조취를 취한다고 봐도 되겠는가?
네
Yes.
나라가 분열된다면
우리에게는 기회입니다
A divided empire
is an opportunity.
One that must be seized upon
with ruthless force.
그러니 강력한 무력으로
기회를 잡아야지요
우리에게 복종하도록
만들 수도 있소
One that can be
molded to serve us.
시다오는 농민 출신이다
Sidao is a peasant...
Empress a grieving widow.
태후는 슬픔에 빠진 과부지
그 부군의 뜻을 충실하게 따르지요
A grieving widow
loyal to the memory of her husband.
죽은 황제는 항상
전쟁을 꺼려했습니다
The dead Emperor
was always a reluctant warrior.
어떤 쪽이 휴전을 제안했을까?
Which hand offers the parley?
어느 쪽이든
Either way,
무엇을 상대하는지 알고
it is better to
know what we face...
이를 통해
전투를 하지 않고
and win the war
with this knowledge
전쟁을 승리하는 것이 낫다
before we consider the battlefield.
협상에 응한다
We parley.
See what the table presents us.
어떤 것을 제안하는지 보자
머리가 똥으로 가득찬
다섯살 꼬맹이가 나올 테고
Perhaps there will be
a dung- stuffed head of a five- year- old.
Then we will have our answer.
그럼 답을 얻을 수 있겠지
아마드
Ahmad...
네가 송의 대사와
협상을 이끌어라
you will lead the parley
with the Song ambassadors.
Depart at dawn.
동틀 때 출발하라
Sire...
폐하
진금 황자님을
보내시는 게 어떻겠습니까?
might I recommend
sending Prince Jingim...
협상이 황명에 의한 것임을
보여주시는 겁니다
so the parley has some
semblance of royal command?
진금 황자는
회담을 지켜보라
Prince Jingim will
oversee the conference.
임무를 명예롭게 받들겠습니다
You honor me
with this task.
중재를 위한 사절이 되어
우창 전투에서의 상처를
Heal the battle wounds
of Wuchang, Jingim...
치유하도록 하라, 황자
as a diplomat making peace.
비밀 임무에는
절대 못 나서겠다
Never volunteer
for a stealth mission.
너 대신 짖을 개를
데려가는 것도 낫겠다
You might as well
have a barking dog accompany you.
- 검을 주십시오
- 라틴인은 다들 너처럼 멍청하냐?
- I need my sword.
- Are all Latins as dense as you?
네게 검을 주겠다
I would give you a sword...
하지만 소문이 돌게 되면 너의 검이
but I'm afraid whose body
the blade would find
when the rumors reach you.
누굴 베게 될지 두렵구나
네 아버지가 돌아왔다
Your father has returned.
대칸이시여
Great Khan,
아라비아 반도의 진귀하고
이국적인 선물입니다
a rare and exotic gift
from the Arabian Peninsula
둔황의 길을 통해 들여왔습니다
by route of Dunhuang.
동물의 똥냄새가 진동하는구나
Animal smells of shit.
몇 주간 저희의 마차에
실려 있었습니다, 대칸
It has been aboard our caravan
for weeks, Great Khan.
Rise.
일어나라
A caravan we humbly
take through your kingdom.
그 마차로 황공하게도
폐하의 제국을 돌아다녔습니다
A kindness we wish to continue,
if your wisdom should allow us.
폐하의 영명함으로 이를
계속 할 수 있었으면 합니다
Prosperous business
is always welcome.
장사가 번영한다면
환영할 일이다
기꺼이 조공을
바치겠습니다, 칸
We gladly gave tribute,
Lord Khan.
그대들의 무역은
계속하도록 하라
You shall be allowed
to continue your trade.
My realm is yours.
자유롭게 다니도록 하라
아들은 관심이 없는가?
Do you have
any interest in your son?
그럼요, 폐하
어서 안아보고 싶습니다
Yes, Sire.
I am anxious to embrace him.
본 지 오래 되었으니까요
It has been too long.
그러면 돌아서서
아들을 보라
Then turn, merchant, and behold.
동양인처럼 보이는구나
You look like an Oriental.
One must adapt to survive, brother.
살기 위해서는
받아들여야지
마르코는 그랬다
And Marco has.
그러면 자신의 유산을
버리지 않아아지요
One can adapt
without forsaking his heritage...
아비의 유산 말이오
his father's heritage.
내 아버지는
아들을 버렸습니다
My father forsook his son.
- 네 심정은 이해...
- 아버진 이해 못하세요!
- I understand your...
- You understand nothing!
널 놔두고 간 건 미안하다
I am sorry I had to leave you,
- 하지만 비단길이 더 위험...
- 왜 돌아온 겁니까?
but it is more dangerous
on the Silk Road...
Why did you return?
이윤을 저축하고, 조공을 바치고
무엇보다 너를 보러 왔다
To bank profits, pay tribute,
mostly to see my boy.
Is that not enough?
그걸로 부족하냐?
그거면 충분합니다
It is enough.
It's not believable.
그럴듯하지 않을 뿐이죠
There are reasons
why we left you.
우리가 널 놔두고 간 이유가 있다
비단길로 다시
돌아가야 했던 이유다
Reasons we must again
return to the Silk Road.
- Commerce.
- No.
- 무역 때문이겠죠
- 아니다
날 믿어야 한다
You must trust me when I say
내가 한 모든 일은 우리 고향과
주와 너를 위한 것이다
all efforts that I make are for
our home... our Lord and for you.
도와주실 게 있어요
I need your help.
말만 하거라
Say it and it is done.
아버지의 칼을 주십시오
Give me your blade.
무엇 때문에?
For what purpose?
이건 사고가 아니에요
This was not an accident.
- 무슨 말썽에 휘말린 거냐?
- 삼촌이 상관할 게 아닙니다
- What trouble have you got into?
- It is no concern of yours.
왜 칼이 필요한 것이냐, 마르코?
What requires a sword, Marco?
누군가 위험에 처했습니다
Someone is in danger.
- 누구?
- 친구요
- Someone?
- A friend.
여자냐?
A woman?
마르코, 내 말 듣거라
Marco, listen to me.
네 옷이며 외양이 닮아도
넌 저들이 아니다
Despite your dress and visage,
you are not one of them.
절대 저들이 되지 못한다
You never will be.
저들과 관계를 맺으면
우리가 다친다
You get involved with them,
you damage us.
가문의 일에
타격을 주는 거다
You damage the family business.
아예 안 갈 줄 알았네요
I thought he would never go.
언젠가는 이해할 겁니다
One day, he will understand.
Your chest is puffed.
가슴을 한껏 내미는군
이런 곳에서는
In this place,
창녀들이 하고 싶을 때나
그러고 다니오
that's what whores do
when they want to get fucked.
머리를 민 기수 말이오
어디 있소?
The horseman with the shaved head,
where is he?
캄불락의 반이 그렇소
That's half of Cambulac.
This one deals in jewels
he could not rightfully own.
그가 원 주인이 아닌
보석을 거래하는 자요
캄불락의 나머지 반이 그러지
That's the other half of Cambulac.
- 그럼 꺼지시오
- 내가 누구 말하는지 알 거요
Now, piss off.
You know who I speak of.
어디서 찾을 수 있는지 말해요
Tell me where I can find him.
내 찻집에 무장도
하지 않고 들어온 건가?
Did you enter
my tea house unarmed?
대답해!
Answer me!
Tell me where!
어딘지 말해!
남쪽 끝이오
The south end.
철로 만든 오두막이오
The shanty by the ironworks.
거짓말이라면
다시 돌아올 거다
If you're lying,
I will come back.
그러시든지
Please do.
왜 코카친을 위협하지?
Why do you threaten Kokachin?
초원에서 당신이
보석을 가져가던 걸 봤다
I saw you on the grasslands.
I saw you take the jewels.
그게 당신과
무슨 상관이지?
What concern is it of yours?
난 코카친을 위협한 적 없어!
당신이 날 쫓아왔잖아
I threatened Kokachin with nothing!
You pursued me.
당신이 위험하다고 생각했어
그분을 위해서는 목숨도 바칠 거다!
I thought you the danger.
I would lay down my life for her.
뭐하는 거야? 안돼!
What are you doing? No!
놔! 놓으라고!
Let me go!
Let me go! Now!
놓으라고! 안돼!
- Let me go!
- No!
실수하는 거요!
You're making a mistake.
유세프 부섭정께 말하시오
그럼 그분이 말씀할 거요
Tell Vice Regent Yusuf where I am.
He will tell you.
그분의 명령이다
It's on his orders.
You did this.
삼촌 짓이군요
아니다
No.
저 쓰레기들이 한 짓이다
Those savages did this,
우린 아무 것도 안 했다
though we did nothing.
네가 같이 사는 저 개들
Those dogs you live with,
they don't know
how to treat men of God.
신의 사람을
어찌 대하는지 모른다
- 우린...
- 밀수를 했다
- We were...
- Smuggling.
밀수를 했다
We were smuggling.
아이에게 더 이상
거짓말할 이유가 없어
There is no point
lying to the boy.
그러면 저들이
어떻게 하는지 아십니까?
Do you know
what they do for that?
난 여기 왜 있는 겁니까?
Why am I here?
어딘가에 물건을
보관해야 했다
We had to store
the goods somewhere.
동전 말이다, 아들아
The coin, son.
날 낯선 땅에
버리고 가 놓고선...
You left me
in this foreign land...
이젠 날 죽이려 하는군요
and now you have destroyed me.
아직도 모르겠습니까?
Do you not see that?
아버진 겁쟁이에요
You're a coward.
평생 동안
All my life
위대한 탐험가가 자신의 옆자리를
나에게 주길 바라왔습니다
I have waited for the great adventurer
to offer me a place at his side.
드디어 내가 원하는 걸 얻었어요
I finally got what I wanted.
시다오는 오지 않았습니까?
Sidao is not here?
애석하기도 그렇습니다
With regret, no.
그쪽의 칸께서도
애석하게도 같은 이유로
Surely, the same regret
the Great Khan offers
for not attending.
오지 않으셨나 봅니다
난 그분의 아들이자 후계자고
그분을 대표하여 말할 것이오
I am his son and heir
and I speak with full authority.
황자님, 저 또한 성벽 도시를
대표하여 말합니다
And I, Prince,
speak with authority from the Walled City.
그 대표 권한은
누구에게서 나왔소?
And from whose authority
does that flow?
The child, the old woman,
or the pretender?
아이? 늙은 여인?
아니면 권력을 탐하는 자?
모든 송 조정을
대표합니다
I speak on behalf of
all the Song dynasty.
한강 밑에서 갈갈이 찢겨있는
남은 잔당들을 말하겠지
You mean all that remains
by a shred of silk
down by the Han River.
그대들의 협상 요청을
진지하게 생각하고 있소
We take your request
for parley with seriousness.
그런 의미로
As a gesture of such,
칸께서는 우창에서 잡은 포로를
석방하실 것이오
the Great Khan releases
our prisoners of war from Wuchang to you.
호의에 감사드립니다
Your gesture is greatly appreciated.
So was yours.
그대들의 호의도 마찬가집니다
Though returning our prisoners
without their bodies
물론 죄수를 시체 없이
돌려보내는 것은
was an interesting prelude for peace.
평화의 서곡으로는
상당히 흥미롭더군요
A regrettable circumstance of war
전쟁으로 인한
유감스러운 상황입니다
그런 일이 되풀이되지
않길 바랍니다
and one we wish not to repeat.
그점엔 동의한 것이오
We are in agreement.
And my father's minister will capitulate.
내 아버님의 재상도
이에 동의할 것이오
당연히 그래야지요
Of course.
적절한 협상안과 위로금이
제공된다면 말입니다
Provided suitable terms
and tribute payments are offered.
- 우리 쪽에서는...
- 은 5십만량
We are prepared to offer...
Five hundred thousand
taels of silver.
bolts of silk.
비단 50만 필
And three of every
five grains of rice you sow...
그리고 그대들이 심은
곡식의 3/5를
10년간 바치시오
for 10 years.
이건 말이 안 됩니다
우린 호의로 이 협상을 제의했습니다
This is beyond reason.
We called for this parley in good faith.
You called for this parley in fear.
두려움 때문에
협상을 제의한 것이지요
양쪽이 존중할 만한
협상을 하기 싫다면
If you do not wish to
engage in honorable terms,
- 다시 돌아가시...
- 대사
- we will return to...
- Ambassador,
이 수치는 부당하긴 하오
this rate is unwarranted.
적당한 규모를 찾을 것이오
We will find a suitable figure.
아마드 재상께서는
호송대와 함께 기다리시오
And Minister Ahmad will wait
with the convoy by the horses.
위대한 쿠빌라이 칸께서는
남중국과의 평화를 바라십니다
The Great Kublai Khan
is interested in peace with South China.
그분이 요구하는 건 건 송 왕조가
역사에 굴복하는 것 뿐입니다
All he demands is that your leaders
surrender the Song dynasty to history.
Become unified with the North
in a new dynasty under a new emperor.
북쪽과 통일하여 새 왕조에서
새 황제를 모시는 것 말이오
이 협상은 왕족의 일입니다
This message
is a burden of royalty.
그러니 재상보단
내가 더 적격이지요
One better suited to myself
than the Minister.
황자님의 한족의 문화와 방식에 대한
존중은 익히 잘 알고 있습니다
Your respect for Chinese ways and culture
is known to us, Prince.
저희는 아직 이 제국의
방식을 잘 모릅니다
We are still new to
the ways of your kingdom.
금전적 가치가 그대들이
가장 먼저 찾는 것이지
Value is the first thing you seek.
위험은 그 다음이고
Risk, the second.
이 누에는 성스러운 것이며
The silk worm is sacred,
보석이나 금보다
더 가치있는 것이다
more valuable
than gems and gold, Master Polo.
이를 훔치는 것은
죽음으로 죄값을 치른다
Its theft is punishable by death.
- 용서하십시오, 저희는 모르고...
- 그만하세요!
Please... we did not know...
Enough.
어디에서 난 것이냐?
What is their origin?
저희가 얻은 것이 아닙니다
They were not procured by us.
저희 일행 중 하나가
얻은 것입니다
A man in our caravan
acquired them.
그 자는 어디 있는가?
Where is this man now?
여로에서 살아남지
못하였습니다, 칸
He did not survive the journey,
Lord Khan.
그대들도 살아남지
못할 듯하구나
And I'm quite confident
neither shall you.
전령이 도착했습니다, 재상님
여동생께서 보냈습니다
A dispatch has arrived, Chancellor.
From your sister.
방금 위대하고 고귀한
쿠빌라이 칸이
I've just received word that
the great and noble Kublai Khan
will not be attending
my peace parley.
내 평화 협상에
못 온다는 소식을 들었습니다
무슨 협상입니까?
What parley?
무슨 짓을 한 거요?
What have you done?
그대는 더 이상 조정에
발을 들일 수 없다
You no longer hold a place
in the Royal Court.
늙은이
Old woman,
그댄 내게 명령하거나
내 자리를 뺏을 권한이 없소
you have no authority
to dictate or declare my place.
내 대사는 어떻게서든 몽골과
합의하라는 지시를 받고 갔다
My ambassadors were instructed to secure
an accord with the Mongols at all costs.
저들이 돌아오면
내게 권한이 주어지고
When they return,
I will have every authority
그대 혼자만 전쟁에
미친 걸 보게 될 것이다
and you will find yourself
a lonely warmonger.
그대의 무기는
전쟁에 대한 두려움이었다
Your currency is the fear of war.
하지만 그것이 바닥나면
그댄 아무것도 아니다
But it is spent
and you are nothing without it.
송은 곡식을 몽골의 배부른 개들과
나누면 안 될 것이오
The Song shall not share rice
with that bloated Mongolian cur.
조정은 평화 제안을
받아들일 것이다
The Council will
embrace peace if offered.
남중국의 백성들은
주군의 뜻을 따를 것이다
The people of South China
will do their Lord's bidding.
그대도 마찬가지여야 할 것이다
And so will you.
풀어라
Unchain him.
물러가라
Leave us.
네 아버지에 대해 말해보라
Tell me of your father.
아버지는...
He...
평판이 좋은 무역상입니다
He is a well- regarded trader.
그분의 선박 거래상은
오랫동안 거래를 유지하고 있습니다
His shipping contacts
have remained loyal through the years.
그자의 성격을 물었는데
그자의 일에 대해 말하는구나
I ask of character
and you tell me of his profession.
너희 언어엔 네 아비를
표현할 말이 없는 것이냐?
Do you have any of your colorful language
that speaks to the man or not?
교묘한 말일 것입니다, 주군
It would be artful color, My Lord.
신기루입니다
A mirage.
어릴 때부터 위대한 징기스의
이야기를 듣고 자랐다
I grew hearing tales
of the Great Genghis.
아주 어릴 때만
그분을 봐 왔지만
I knew him only as a small boy,
내가 본 그 분은
그리 크지 않았다
but the man my eyes saw
was not big enough.
내 마음 속 징기스께선...
Genghis of my mind...
거인이셨다
he was a giant.
상상이 우리 자신을
넘어선 것입니다, 폐하
Our imaginations outrun us, Sire.
그대가 캄불락에 왔고
아비가 그댈 내게 줬을 때
When you made your way to Cambulac
and your father left you to me,
이 동쪽으로는 더 가지 못했지?
you had gone no further east,
had you?
그렇습니다
No.
이 누에는...
These silkworms...
젠시 지방이 원산지다
they are native
to the Jiangxi province.
그대가 가보지 못한 곳이지
A region you have never visited.
하지만 네 아비와 숙부는
그곳으로 갔다
But your father and uncle
have since traveled there.
이 고치로 비단을 만든다
It's the cocoon
that gives the silk.
달콤한 젖처럼 나오다가
딱딱해지지
Comes out like sweet milk, then hardens.
못생긴 애벌레는
못생긴 나방으로 자라나지만...
Ugly worm turns
into an ugly moth, but...
아주 소중한
보물을 남겨놓지
leaves such treasure behind.
어딘가에서 꼬마들은
나방을 죽이지만...
Then some child somewhere
crushes the moth, but...
비단은 여전히 내것이다
the silk is still mine.
이 벌레...
The worm...
비단....
the silk...
그 아이들도...
the child...
모두 내 것이다
All mine.
너는 살려두마
You will be spared.
네 아비와 숙부는
벌을 받을 것이다
Your father and uncle
will be sentenced.
교묘한 말로도 저들의
성격을 달라지게 하진 않는다
Artful color will not
alter their character.
벌은 무엇입니까?
What is their punishment?
그것은 생각해보고 있다
It is on this that I dwell.
싸웠군요
You've been fighting.
스파이가 날 쫓았습니다
A spy, he tracked me.
누구였어요?
Who was it?
외국인이었습니다
눈이 동그란 놈이고요
A foreigner.
A round eye.
위험하지 않을 겁니다
He is no threat.
황실 근위대가 체포했습니다
The Imperial Guard arrested him.
뱀을 놔두실 필요는 없었습니다
You did not need
to set the snake.
- 근위대가 잡아갔다면...
- 놈은 아무것도 모릅니다
If the Guard have him...
He knows nothing.
제가 공주님을 해치려 했다
생각하더군요
He thought I was trying to hurt you,
공주님에게서 물건을 훔쳤다고요
to steal from you.
그자가 날 지키려 했군요
And he tried to defend me.
왜 그런 겁니까?
Why would he do that?
나도 몰라요
I do not know.
하지만 그대의 마음은 알아요
다른 이에게 맘을 주진 않아요
But I know your mind.
I turn my heart to no other.
보석 거래는 잘 끝났습니다
이젠 가도 됩니다
The gems have traded well.
We should go.
기다려요
Patience.
전쟁이 다가오고 있어요
War is coming.
그 사이에 빠져나갈
기회가 생길 거예요
We will find cover
for our escape within it.
송에선 서방에 대한
습격을 중단하며
The Song have agreed
to cease their raids in the west
조공을 바칠 것을
약속했습니다, 아버님
and pay tribute to you, Father.
피를 흘리지 않고
평화를 얻어냈습니다
Peace without bloodshed
is upon us.
평화 교섭을 어디에서 했는지
짐작이 되더냐?
Was there a sense of where
the parley offer came from?
누가 협상을 지시했느냐?
Who is the administering hand?
To this end,
the Minister was wise to inquire.
이를 위해 재상께서
직접 물었으나
They artfully evaded a direct answer.
아주 영리하게
즉답을 피했습니다
But it would be safe
to assume the Walled City is caught
하지만 최소한
성벽 도시에서
지아 시다오 재상과
태후 간의 권력 다툼이
amidst a power struggle
between the Chancellor Jia Sidao
있는 것은 확실합니다
and the Empress Dowager.
새새끼들이 패배를 두고
싸우는 동안
Let the yellow birds
battle over their defeat
while we celebrate
the well- crafted victory of Prince Jingim.
우리는 진금 왕자의
승리를 축하하자
그러겠습니다
Yes.
참 못생긴 것도 다 있죠
Such an ugly little creature.
Yet men will kill for it.
그래도 어떻게든
이걸 얻으려 하지
내 분노를 사고...
Risk my wrath.
Betray their blood.
핏줄도 배신하였소
그들에게는...
Because to them...
유산이 아닌 재물이
삶을 바꾸기 때문이야
it is fortune, not legacy,
that changes a life.
이리 오시오
Come to me.
왜 그러오?
What is wrong?
놀라서 그럽니다
I'm simply surprised.
왜?
By?
요즘 폐하의 관심은
그 한족 여인에게...
Your attention these days
seems to be occupied with...
가 있는 것 같아서요
Chinese matters.
아...
Ah.
그래...
Yes.
한족 여인들은...
These Chinese, they...
주의깊은 관심이 필요하지
require careful attention.
그러니 가까이 두고
지켜봐야 할 듯하오
Well, I should...
have to watch her close.
대칸께는 어려운 일이
아닐 것입니다
Not something the Great Khan
should be troubled with.
좀 더 이국적인
아이들을 찾아볼까요?
Let me find you
someone more exotic.
인도인이나
An Indian.
잔지바르인?
A Zanzibari.
슬라브인은 어떻습니까?
Perhaps, a Slav.
그애는...
It's her...
기량은 있는 듯하나
그것이 활용되는 방법이...
Her prowess is evident,
yet simply not harnessed in the...
아직 적절치 않소
proper manner.
그것은 연습으로
해결할 수 있을 것이오
Something that should be
remedied with much practice.
걱정할 것 없소
내가 가장 아끼는 아내여
You worry without cause,
my lovely, favorite wife.
그대는 그 누구보다
우선이오
You have a place
above all others.
형식적으로는 그렇죠
Ceremonially.
차브이...
Chabi...
그대를 깊이 사랑하오
you have my devotion.
이제 진금이 가져온 중국에 대한
몽골의 승리를 축하하셔야죠
It is time to honor
Jingim's Mongol triumph over the Chinese.
네 어머니가 오늘 소식을 보냈다
Your mother sent a message today.
아주 중요한 소식인데
늦게 도착했구나
An important message
that arrived too late.
손실이 컸다
It cost me greatly.
하지만 내가 운이 좋았다
But luck was with me.
네 어머니의 실패를
내 기회로 바꿨다
I turned your mother's failure
to my favor.
하지만 실수는 바로잡아야지
Still, mistakes demand correction.
자기 전에 내가
이야기해줄 게 있다
I have a tale to tell you
before sleep.
귀뚜라미 재상이다
귀뚜라미 재상이야
It's the Cricket Minister.
뛰는 것 보아라
뛰는 걸 봐
Look how they leap.
내 승자인 아들!
A victorious son!
아마드!
Ahmad!
아주 오래 전...
Long ago...
요낭이라는 후궁이
이욱 황제의 총애를 받았단다
the consort Yao Niang
was the favorite of Emperor Li Yu.
그녀도 너처럼 춤을 잘 췄지
She was a dancer, like you.
이욱 황제는...
Emperor Yu believed
발이 여성의 아름다움의
정수라고 여겼단다
that a woman's feet were
the very essence of feminine beauty.
그래서 요낭을
좋아했단다
This is why
he liked Yao Niang.
그 발은 작고
섬세하고 완벽했거든
Her feet were small,
delicate, perfect.
그런 발을 가진 여인들은
많은 곳에서 탐냈단다
Women with such feet
became coveted.
발 크기를 유지하기 위해
여러 조치를 취했지
Measures had to be taken
to keep their feet the perfect size.
세 마디 길이로...
Three inches long.
묶어야 했단다
They had to be bound.
저렇게 된 게 아니지 않습니까
That is not
how that happened.
평화로운 합의를 끌어낸 걸
축하드립니다
I congratulate you, brother,
on a fine accord.
전투뿐 아니라 정치에서도
능력을 인정받으셨소
You are now proven
in battle and politics.
전사이자 외교관으로 말이오
Warrior and diplomat.
협상에서 제가 지나친 것에
용서를 구합니다
And I beg forgiveness if I,
at all, overstepped at the parley.
황자님의 일이지
제 일이 아니었습니다
It was your hour, not mine.
그대의 공세가
송의 힘을 빼 놓았소
Your aggression weakened the Song.
늑대와 까마귀처럼 말이오
Wolf and crow, Ahmad.
전 장부나 쓸 뿐입니다
I am just a bookkeeper.
셈을 하고, 장부를 적고
폐하를 섬기지요
I tally, I account, I serve.
우리가 한 일이오
It was our day.
Were we born of the same mother,
우리가 같은 어머니
밑에서 태어났어도
we could not have worked
together better as brothers.
형제처럼 어울려서
일을 하진 못했을 거요
린넨 천을...
A piece of linen...
is wrapped
over the four small toes...
작은 발가락 4개에 감고...
발등 밑으로 당긴 후
pulled under the instep
발꿈치 뒤로 돌린단다
and behind the heel.
오너라
Come.
그리고 이 천을...
Now, this linen...
발가락이 부러질 때까지
매일 당기고...
is tightened daily
until the toes break,
발 밑으로 접어서
fold under the foot
발바닥에 대고
평평하게 만든단다
and flatten themselves
against the sole.
발꿈치는 시간이 지날수록
평평해지고...
The heel becomes slender over time.
마침내...
And finally...
발꿈치가 발볼 쪽으로 옮겨지고
the heel shifts forward
to the ball of the foot,
발허리를 부러뜨려
위로 향하게 한단다
breaking the arch
and forcing it upward.
황후마마
My Lady.
칸께서 만족하지 않으신다
The Khan is dissatisfied.
그 말씀을 들으니
고통스럽습니다
I am pained
to hear such news.
그래야 할 것이다
As well you should be.
내게 보여달라
Show me.
마마?
Empress?
그대가 어떻게 하는지 보여라
Show me how you move.
그대의 흠을
내가 치유할 것이다
I will remedy your flaws.
그렇게 신성시되는 여인이
될 수 있을 것 같느냐?
Do you think you would like to be
one of these hallowed women?
그 아름다운 요낭처럼?
Like the beautiful dancer Yao Niang?
재상님
Chancellor?
왜?
Yes?
네 어미가 오래 전
이걸 해야만 했다
Your mother should have
started this years ago.
네 어미가 한 짓이다
She causes you this pain.
가만히 있거라, 해바라기야
Be still, my Sunflower.
가만히 있어
Be still.
We are your ambassadors.
우린 그대들의 사신이오
Please! Mercy!
We are Song!
제발 살려주시오
송 사람이오!
이런 희생은 칸께서
의도하신 계략이겠지요
I expect that sacrifice was a ruse
the Great Khan had intended.
흠
Hmm.
아비가 걱정되느냐?
Do you worry for your father?
아비가 스스로 화를
자초한 것입니다
My father brought
his plight upon himself.
저도 압니다
I know this.
잠을 이룰 수가 없지?
It keeps sleep at bay, hmm?
어렸을 때부터
겪을 고통이었습니다
A persistent affliction
since I was a boy.
그것 때문에
네가 밤에
And is it this affliction
that sees you roaming
말을 달린 것이냐?
at night on horseback?
The canals called to me at home.
Here, the grasslands.
고향에선 운하가 저를 불렀고
여기선 초원이 그렇습니다
필적할 것이 없는
괴로움이지
It is a demon like no other.
머리를 뉘는 어느 곳에서든
잠이 드는 자는
One who sleeps
wherever he lays his head
그 짐을 이해하지 못한다
can never understand the beast.
You, too, My Lord?
폐하도 그러하십니까?
통치의 어지러움이 잠들 때
내 머리를 가득 채운다
The distractions of rule
occupy my mind when I should sleep.
You are a thinker, Latin,
as am I.
라틴인 넌 생각을 하지
나도 마찬가지다
그게 좋은 것이다
This is good.
네 아버지의 죄는
대가를 치러야 한다
Amends must be made
for your father's crime.
알고 있습니다
I understand.
네가 그의 운명을 결정하라
You will decide his fate.
폐하?
My Lord?
내 부섭정 유세프나
내 스스로 생각해도
Left to my vice regent, Yusuf,
or myself,
네 아버지는 당연히
처벌받아야 한다
your father's punishment
would be certain.
뭔가를 훔치려는 마음은
없어져야 할 것이다
His thief heart would now be still.
이게 네게 고통을
가져올 걸 알고 있다
I know the pain this will cause you.
난 연민이 무엇인지 안다
I know compassion.
대신 넌 우리 법을 알고...
And you know our laws...
우리 관습을 안다
our customs.
네가 네 아버지의
벌을 정하라
You will choose
your father's punishment.
그러면 잠을
이룰 수 있을 것이다
And then you shall find sleep.
Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com